<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Mike Borozdin&#39;s Blog</title>
    <description>software engineering, product management &amp; agile
</description>
    <link>https://mikeborozdin.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://mikeborozdin.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 16 Oct 2018 21:28:16 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 16 Oct 2018 21:28:16 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Value Hypothesis and KPIs</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This post talks about setting a value hypothesis and related KPIs. It’s part of &lt;a href=&quot;/product-management-in-the-open&quot;&gt;the ‘Product Management in the Open’ series&lt;/a&gt;. The goal of the series is describe the process of product managing a mobile app - Best in Town / Best in Edinburgh. Please, &lt;a href=&quot;/product-management-in-the-open/idea&quot;&gt;check this page to read more about the app itself&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post describes my thinking back in the beginning of 2017. Not everything I did at that time was correct and I also try to reflect on some of the mistakes here.&lt;!-- more --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;value-hypothesis&quot;&gt;Value Hypothesis&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, so we’ve got a product idea. But how do we know if it’s a good idea?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, what we’ve got is called a &lt;em&gt;value hypothesis&lt;/em&gt; in the Lean Startup terminology. We just have a hypothesis that people will like the idea of an app that rates meals &amp;amp; drinks as opposed to entire venues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;build-measure-learn-loop&quot;&gt;Build-Measure-Learn Loop&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any hypothesis has to be validated. That takes to another concept from the Lean Startup - ‘&lt;em&gt;Build-Measure-Learn&lt;/em&gt;’ loop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/product-management-in-the-open/value-hypothesis/build-measure-learn.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Build-Measure-Learn Loop&quot; class=&quot;center-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We come up with an idea&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We define a hypothesis to validate it&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We identify the KPIs that allow us to test the hypothesis&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We build a very minimal product to validate it&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And finally we can either confirm or deny our hypothesis
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Next blog posts though will tell that the process of validating a hypothesis is not as straightforward as it sounds here&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;critical-action&quot;&gt;Critical Action&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So our hypothesis is that people will use Best in Town. Or in other words, they will use a mobile app that shows rates meals &amp;amp; drinks, instead of entire places. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what does it really mean ‘to use a product’? Does it mean that people download it? Open it? Or do something else?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we said before, users must get a value out of the product. And that means more than just installing an app or launching it. It means performing &lt;em&gt;a critical action&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A classic example of a critical action is playing a song in a music player app. Indeed, if people open the music player app, but don’t play a song, it means they don’t get a value out of it. Of course, there could be a case when the value users get is different from what the creators perceived. For example, people use the music player app to read lyrics instead of playing songs. And if we can spot that trend, we can change our app, so that it focuses on songs lyrics. Such a change in direction is called &lt;em&gt;pivoting&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When it comes to Best in Edinburgh, &lt;em&gt;the critical action is looking at the place&lt;/em&gt;. In other words, someone has chosen a category, for example, ‘Best wine’ and opened any place on the map. That shows that they are looking at the best places to go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;could-there-be-another-critical-action&quot;&gt;Could There Be Another Critical Action?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we define a critical action as an the main action that gives a value, then we can take it even further. We can say that a critical action is an act of physically getting to a place after looking it up on Best in Town. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That would be the best indicator if people are finding the app valuable. However, it will be quite challenging to measure that in the context of a Minimum Viable Product (MVP).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;kpi---retention&quot;&gt;KPI - Retention&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, we’ve established the critical action - opening a place. But is it enough to measure? Let’s say all, people who’ve downloaded the app, opened the place - would it tell us that users find it useful? What if they only do it once? What if people only use the app once after installing it? Then, perhaps they don’t find the app that useful, after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;engagement-apps-vs-transactional-ones&quot;&gt;Engagement Apps vs Transactional Ones&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be completely fair, the last statement could be debated. In theory, there can be an app that solves a user’s needs once and for all. In that case, it’ll be unwise to expect people to come back to the same app again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, there can be products that are transactional in nature - people use them to buy something or order a taxi. Of course, a good retention would be absolutely invaluable for that kind of apps, too. But it may not be the top KPI for them. Instead, a better KPI could be a percentage of people who complete a transaction versus just browsing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe Best in Edinburgh / Best in Town falls into a different category of apps - ‘engagement apps’ (for the lack of a better word). They meant to be constantly provider a value to a user, albeit not necessarily on daily basis. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;different-kinds-of-retention-and-usage-patterns&quot;&gt;Different Kinds of Retention and Usage Patterns&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what we are looking for is recurring users who keep coming back. We’re looking for user retention. And when it comes to retention there are three different types of it - Daily, Weekly, and Monthly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to choose a retention type we need to understand the usage patterns of the app. It might be tempting to think that people will use your app every day. But that’s very often not the case. There are successful apps that have good retention apps but not used daily. And if the app is not meant for an everyday use, then there’s not much point of looking at daily retention rate. Monthly retention may show a more accurate picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Best in Edinburgh fails into that category. It’s not going to be used daily by the same people. There’s  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.quantcast.com/measure/yelp.com#/engagementCard&quot;&gt;a research by QuantCast about Yelp&lt;/a&gt; (a similar app/website) that shows that only 25% of users come to it more than once a month. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plus, there’s also an anecdotal evidence about myself and my friends. We do use Yelp/TripAdvisor/Google Maps for finding new places, but we don’t do it daily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;So, monthly retention is our KPI&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;setting-kpi-retention-goals&quot;&gt;Setting KPI (Retention) Goals&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But which retention are we looking to get - 100%, 50%, 25%? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the time when I was setting that goal - early 2016 - I did research on the average monthly retention rate for mobile apps. And I discovered the following.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://info.localytics.com/blog/mobile-apps-whats-a-good-retention-rate&quot;&gt;The Localytics report&lt;/a&gt; that said only 36% people, who downloaded an app, used it a month later. Please, note that if you open that report now, it’ll show higher retention figures that at that time when I was doing this research. Luckily, I copied this chart back then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/product-management-in-the-open/value-hypothesis/localytics-retention-2016.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Localytics Report&quot; class=&quot;center-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also discovered &lt;a href=&quot;https://andrewchen.co/new-data-shows-why-losing-80-of-your-mobile-users-is-normal-and-that-the-best-apps-do-much-better/&quot;&gt;a seminal post by Andrew Chen - ‘New data shows losing 80% of mobile users is normal, and why the best apps do better’&lt;/a&gt; where he quotes figures that says that on average only 10% of users are still with an app 30 days later. That data is better for top 100 apps - 25%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;So based on that, we’ll set out goal to have M1 retention rate of 20%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusion-and-next-steps-taken-in-early-2017&quot;&gt;Conclusion and Next Steps (taken in Early 2017)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, based on the following research and thoughts we conclude the following.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hypothesis:&lt;/strong&gt; People like the idea behind Best in Town / Best in Edinburgh&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hypothesis validation:&lt;/strong&gt; 20% of people who installed an app will come back to perform a critical action a month later&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Critical action:&lt;/strong&gt; opening a place&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;next-steps&quot;&gt;Next Steps&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve determined our hypothesis and how we’re going to measure it. So, the next step would be to build an MVP, as minimal as possible, and get it to users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll describe what will be included in the MPV in the next blog posts, which are coming out soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;reflections-and-possible-mistakes&quot;&gt;Reflections and Possible Mistakes&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writing this in Autumn 2018 I can spot the mistake I made when I setting the goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you look at &lt;a href=&quot;../idea#product-vision-board&quot;&gt;the Product Vision Board&lt;/a&gt;, you’ll see that the app serves two categories of users - Edinburgh locals and visitors. However, when I set the KPI to monthly retention I ignored the visitors group. If we have tourists and business visitors using the app, chances are they won’t come back to the app a month later, because they won’t be in Edinburgh. As a result, we won’t learn from them and they will even negatively skew the statistics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back, that’s one of the mistakes I’ve made. I didn’t know who my target audience would be. I catered for two - local population and visitors. But the KPIs were targeted only to the local population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;additional-resources&quot;&gt;Additional Resources&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://info.localytics.com/blog/mobile-apps-whats-a-good-retention-rate&quot;&gt;Mobile Apps: What’s A Good Retention Rate?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://andrewchen.co/new-data-shows-why-losing-80-of-your-mobile-users-is-normal-and-that-the-best-apps-do-much-better/&quot;&gt;New data shows losing 80% of mobile users is normal, and why the best apps do better&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://clevertap.com/blog/aarrr-metrics-vs-rarra-framework/&quot;&gt;AARRR vs. RARRA: Which is Better? - great post why it’s more important to focus on retention, as opposed to acquisition&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/product-breakdown/product-management-analytics-what-metrics-should-you-be-measuring-241609b1950d&quot;&gt;Product Management &amp;amp; Analytics: what metrics should you be measuring?&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;This post introduces a concept of engagement and transactional apps&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 16 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://mikeborozdin.com/product-management-in-the-open/value-hypothesis-and-kpis</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://mikeborozdin.com/product-management-in-the-open/value-hypothesis-and-kpis</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Idea</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;elevator-pitch&quot;&gt;Elevator Pitch&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A mobile app that helps to find places that do you favourite meal or drink the best. Unlike existing products (Google Maps, TripAdvisor, Yelp), you see ratings for meals &amp;amp; drinks, as opposed to the whole place.&lt;!-- more --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Choose what you’re interested in&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;See places with ratings around you&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Get more info about place&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/product-management-in-the-open/idea/choose-category.png&quot; alt=&quot;Mockup&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/product-management-in-the-open/idea/ratings-on-map.png&quot; alt=&quot;Mockup&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/product-management-in-the-open/idea/place.png&quot; alt=&quot;Mockup&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;product-vision-board&quot;&gt;Product Vision Board&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, I’ve created a Product Canvas that helps to define various aspects about the products - target groups, needs, etc. That’s based on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.romanpichler.com/blog/the-product-canvas/&quot;&gt;the blog post by Roman Pichler&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;
      &lt;strong&gt;Vision&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td colspan=&quot;3&quot;&gt;
      Help to find best things in town (brownies, coffee, wine, dry cleaners)
    &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;
      &lt;strong&gt;Target Groups:&lt;/strong&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Visitors who come into town and search for the best wine&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;People about town who always want to know where the best coffee is&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;
      &lt;strong&gt;Needs:&lt;/strong&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Finding the best thing around me right now&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Finding the best thing (brownie, coffee) in town&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;
      &lt;strong&gt;Product&lt;/strong&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Mobile app&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Unlike other apps it allows searching places by a thing (brownie, coffee, wine)&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;
          When I search for ‘brownie’, I’ll see places list by the quality of brownies, 
          not by the overall quality
        &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Current products (Yelp, TripAdvisor, FourSquare) only show the overall rating&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;But what does it mean for a cafe to be rated 4 stars?&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Does it mean that it’s got a 4 star coffee? Or a brownie? Or just a cozy interior?&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;
      &lt;strong&gt;Business Goals&lt;/strong&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Gain Product Management experience&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Generate revenue&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Sold it to the current incumbents (Yelp, Google, TripAdvisor, Facebook)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 15 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://mikeborozdin.com/product-management-in-the-open/idea</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://mikeborozdin.com/product-management-in-the-open/idea</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Lean Startup and Inspiration</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is the first article in the series about working on a mobile application - Best in Town / Best in Edinburgh - and applying the Lean Startup methodology and other good product management techniques. &lt;!-- more --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few words about myself. I come from a Software Engineering background, but I’ve always had a keen interest in Product Management. I’ve had a chance to be a Product Owner on a few different projects - it was very exciting. And I learnt how to translate a product vision to a roadmap and then to an actual deliverable. However, I didn’t have a chance to do ideation, market research, set up goals and metrics, experiment, pivot, and so on. So, one of the ideas behind my endeavour is to try to do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;how-it-all-started&quot;&gt;How it all Started&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was sitting in a new cafe&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; in a trendy part of Edinburgh, UK and reading the ‘Lean Startup’ by Eric Ries. I was enjoying the vibe in the cafe and the winter sun outside, but I wasn’t impressed with either the coffee or cakes which were on offer. The place was busy though. And TripAdvisor and Yelp both showed a relatively good rating. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last fact led me to a thought - what is a rating on TripAdvisor, Yelp, and the other usual suspects? As a rating you get a single number - 4.1 stars, but what does it really mean? Does it mean that a place has a good coffee? Or maybe the brownies there are delicious? Or could it be a nice atmosphere and staff? Or is it a combination of all those factors?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/product-management-in-the-open/intro/single-rating.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;What is a rating?&quot; class=&quot;center-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hmm… but what if you are really interested in finding places that do coffee the best? Or any other favourite thing of yours? Or say, for example, you have friends over from abroad and want to surprise them with the best craft beer in town? How do you find it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Say, you’re looking for a bar with amazing wine. You search for ‘wine’, but the existing apps will only throw at you a number of French restaurants. Granted, they would have great wine, but it’s not something you’re looking for. You just care about the quality of wine, nothing else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter, Best in Edinburgh (or Best in Town it was known in those days). In Best in Town you can search for specific things - wine, craft beer, coffee, and it’ll show you ratings for those things only. So, if one bar has 5 stars for wine, but only 4 for cocktails, the app will tell you about it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can read more about &lt;a href=&quot;../idea&quot;&gt;the idea itself here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The cafe closed shut at some point that year. It was replaced by another one - Brill Jewellery &amp;amp; Coffee. Yes, it was a both a jewellery shop and a cafe. Nothing to be surprised about though. It was in in Stockbridge, Edinburgh - the most fashionable part of town. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 14 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://mikeborozdin.com/product-management-in-the-open/lean-startup-and-inspiration</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://mikeborozdin.com/product-management-in-the-open/lean-startup-and-inspiration</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Split User Stories Ruthlessly - And Get Value Earlier</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Why do you need to split user stories?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often, you hear that it is important to split user stories. You read articles that say it should be possible to complete a user story within a single sprint, ideally within a few days. That’s entirely accurate. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But the main benefit of splitting user stories is that you will deliver value faster!&lt;!-- more --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s take a look at an example. Say, we are developing a time tracking tool. Its main purpose is to analyse time spent on different projects. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s also assume that we already have a prioritised backlog that looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Enter timesheets&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Approve timesheets&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;View time spent by project&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the first glance, the backlog looks reasonable. It appears to be prioritised and the user stories look small enough. But the devil is in the details. When you look at the the first story - &lt;code&gt;‘Enter timesheets’&lt;/code&gt;, you’ll see the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;As a developer
I want to be able to log time spent on projects
So that the company could analyse time spent on different projects

**Acceptance criteria**

* Users select a project and enter hours spent for each day
* Users can add more lines for other projects
	* Users can delete lines for projects
	* If a user presses [delete] on an item with hours, 
		there has to be a confirmation pop-up
* There should be an area where a user can see total time spent per day
	* We want a user to avoid making mistakes. If time soent is less or more than 
	8 hours per day it has to be coloured in red. 
	If it’s 8 hours plus/minus one hour, it should be coloured in green.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s also a mockup attached.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2017-08-13-split-user-stories/mockup.png&quot; alt=&quot;Mockup&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, that’s escalated quickly! A simple story has turned out into a collection of business rules!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may seem that each rule is small enough and can be easily implemented. But don’t give in to that temptation!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each rule is small enough, but in total they all will make up to a substantial amount of time to develop. That will, in turn, require a good amount of testing, as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;think-of-product-goal&quot;&gt;Think of Product Goal&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, let’s stop and think. What’s the proposition behind your product? It is analysis of time spent on different projects. There is even a user story for that. So, why don’t we go to that user story as fast as possible?!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;consider-main-goal-of-user-story-split-story-to-achive-that-goal-faster&quot;&gt;Consider Main Goal of User Story. Split Story to Achive That Goal Faster&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what is the main premise of the ‘Enter timesheets’ story? Well, that’s an ability to enter timesheets! So, let’s focus on that activity and try to move other bits into separate user stories. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we look at the acceptance criteria, we’ll see that most of it is not about entering timesheets, but related functionality. For example, we want to have a variable number of activities (lines) per week. Then, we would like to see nice visual cues, if hours entered look wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those are great ideas, but do they help us to achive the overacrching product goal? No. So, let’s focus on what is really important. And split the user story into:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Enter timesheets (3 activities per week)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Visual cues when the hours entered doesn’t look right&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have more than 3 activities per week&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;re-prioritise-backlog&quot;&gt;Re-prioritise Backlog&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, we should go back to our backlog and re-prioritise it. We want to put the last two stories to the bottom of the backlog. At the end your backlog should look like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Enter timesheets (3 activities per week)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Approve timesheets&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;View time spent by project&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Visual cues when the hours entered doesn’t look right&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have more than 3 activities per week&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Always re-prioritise the backlog after splitting user stories. Otherwise, you would do the same things in the initial order and wouldn’t move towards your product goals fast enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Splitting user stories allows you to prioritise what is really important. And achieve the product goals faster. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll probably have to repeat this exercise for ‘Approve Timesheets’ and ‘View time spent by project’. But I guess you’ve got the idea. You’ll end up with the &lt;strong&gt;Prioritise - Split - Prioritise cycle&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2017-08-13-split-user-stories/prioritise-split-cycle.png&quot; alt=&quot;Prioritise-Split Cycle&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another good way to look at is to revisit the famous picture of the iterative Mona Lisa (pictures below are credit of Jeff Patton - the inventor of User Story Maps) &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Incremental Mona Lisa&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2017-08-13-split-user-stories/incremental-mona-lisa.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Incremental Mona Lisa&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Iterative Mona Lisa&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2017-08-13-split-user-stories/iterative-mona-lisa.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Iterative Mona Lisa&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, you don’t want to spend time painting the perfect top-left corner of the picture (the original ‘Enter Timesheets’ story). Instead, you want to sketch out the whole piece. That will already give users and stakeholders something to play with. Such early deliver will allow you to get feedback from users and learn from that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;additional-reading&quot;&gt;Additional Reading&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve focused on the benefits of splitting user stories here. But if you want to know more about techniques for splitting user stories and prioritising backlogs, then I would suggest the following reading:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://agileforall.com/patterns-for-splitting-user-stories/&quot;&gt;Patterns for Splitting User Stories&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://jpattonassociates.com/the-new-backlog/&quot;&gt;The New User Story Backlog is a Map&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;User Story Mapping is a fantastic technique for understand how to achieve a user’s goals fast&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.impactmapping.org/delivering.html&quot;&gt;Impact Mapping&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Impact Mapping is especially good at understand what you &lt;strong&gt;don’t need&lt;/strong&gt; to do in order to achieve your goals&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 13 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://mikeborozdin.com/post/split-user-stories-get-value-early</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://mikeborozdin.com/post/split-user-stories-get-value-early</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Writing a JavaScript Public Library? Validate Your Arguments</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;How many times have seen an obscure JavaScript error when using one 3rd party library or another? More likely than not, you’ve come across a message like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;TypeError: Cannot call method &#39;someMethod&#39; of undefined
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your browser or the Node.js interpreter will tell you in which file and on which line that error has occurred. Then, you’ll start a very mundane task of examining the code of a 3rd party library, if it’s has not been minimised, of course. Eventually, you will find out that you have forgotten to provide one of the arguments required by a function.
You may even see a more obscure error. &lt;!-- more --&gt; Let’s take the standard Node.js library for an example, more specifically, its &lt;code&gt;http&lt;/code&gt; module. It has the &lt;code&gt;request()&lt;/code&gt; function that sends an HTTP request that can be meticulously configured with an object you pass into. What if you accidentally confuse one of the object’s attributes, for example, instead of typing &lt;code&gt;hostname&lt;/code&gt; you write &lt;code&gt;url&lt;/code&gt;, e.g.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-javascript&quot; data-lang=&quot;javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;True-1&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;http&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;require&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;http&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name=&quot;True-2&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a name=&quot;True-3&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;req&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;http&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;request&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;({&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name=&quot;True-4&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;url&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;www.google.com&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name=&quot;True-5&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;});&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, you will see an error saying exactly the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;throw er; // Unhandled &#39;error&#39; event
Error: connect ECONNREFUSED
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Urgh, what could it mean? Has Google suddenly gone down? No, you should have read the documentation more carefully and remember that the attribute is called &lt;code&gt;hostname&lt;/code&gt;, not &lt;code&gt;url&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, so, where does the problem lie? Is it a developer’s problem that they have accidentally made mistake and spent hours debugging? Let’s face, we all make mistakes. Some tools though provide better feedback than the other ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;can-static-typing-really-help&quot;&gt;Can Static Typing Really Help?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It might sound that I’m arriving on the idea of introducing static typing in JavaScript - this is not true. However, I believe that when we’re writing code in JavaScript we still assume certain types. In other words, if we create a multiplying function, like the one below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-javascript&quot; data-lang=&quot;javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;True-1&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;multiply&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;b&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name=&quot;True-2&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;	&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;b&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name=&quot;True-3&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We presume that &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;b&lt;/code&gt; are numbers, not strings or objects. This idea is beautifully put by Facebook &lt;a href=&quot;https://code.facebook.com/posts/1505962329687926/flow-a-new-static-type-checker-for-javascript/&quot;&gt;in their introduction to Flow&lt;/a&gt;, a static type checking for JavaScript - &lt;em&gt;‘the design of Flow is the assumption that most JavaScript code is implicitly statically typed; even though types may not appear anywhere in the code, they are in the developer’s mind as a way to reason about the correctness of the code’&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Would even having static typing in JavaScript help? After all, you can already use TypeScript…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, partially… Statically typed languages are still prone to similar issues. Let’s take Java as an example. It can provide great feedback to a developer during a compilation. What about the run time though? How many time have you seen a &lt;code&gt;NullPointerException&lt;/code&gt; creeping out of nowhere?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is Java’s &lt;code&gt;NullPointerException&lt;/code&gt; anyhow different from the problem with &lt;code&gt;undefined&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;null&lt;/code&gt; in JavaScript? Not really. Either way, you’ll have to analyse a call stack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider the following example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-java&quot; data-lang=&quot;java&quot;&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;True-1&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;CustomerPrinter&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name=&quot;True-2&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;printCustomerInfo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;final&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Customer&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;customer&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name=&quot;True-3&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;   &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;System&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;out&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;println&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;customer&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;getName&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;());&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name=&quot;True-4&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name=&quot;True-5&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The code is written in a statically type language, so you cannot pass an &lt;code&gt;int&lt;/code&gt; or a &lt;code&gt;String&lt;/code&gt;. What about passing a &lt;code&gt;null&lt;/code&gt; though?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-java&quot; data-lang=&quot;java&quot;&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;True-1&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;CustomerPrinter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;().&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;printCustomerInfo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kc&quot;&gt;null&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That problem will not be caught when compiling the code, instead there will be a runtime exception. The code snippet above is fairly simple. Imagine calling &lt;code&gt;customer.getName()&lt;/code&gt; somewhere deep inside the method? That would be ‘fun’ to debug…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s hardly a surprise that even Java, a statically typed language, has libraries, such as Guava, one of which goals is to solve the problem by &lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/26184322/whats-the-point-of-guava-checknotnull&quot;&gt;failing fast&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developers, using Guava, would strive to use &lt;code&gt;Preconditions&lt;/code&gt; to fail as early as possibly and provide meaningful information if something goes wrong, e.g.:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-java&quot; data-lang=&quot;java&quot;&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;True-1&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;CustomerPrinter&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name=&quot;True-2&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;printCustomerInfo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;final&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Customer&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;customer&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name=&quot;True-3&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;   &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Preconditions&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;checkNotNull&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;customer&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name=&quot;True-4&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a name=&quot;True-5&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;   &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;System&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;out&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;println&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;customer&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;getName&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;());&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name=&quot;True-6&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name=&quot;True-7&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fail-fast&quot;&gt;Fail Fast&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, we arrive on a very important point when it comes to the API design. Do fail fast. Please, do. I also beg you to provide an informative message to a user. We all use 3rd party libraries because they solve problems we don’t want to specialise in. And we don’t want to dive into the code of those libraries to find out why we see that message about some undefined value or something even more esoteric.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All we want to see is a nice message saying that a certain argument is not what a function expects. That can be implemented with a fairly simple piece of code:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-javascript&quot; data-lang=&quot;javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;True-1&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;sendHttpRequest&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;params&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name=&quot;True-2&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;typeof&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;params&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;!==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;object&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;||&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;typeof&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;params&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;hostname&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;!==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;string&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name=&quot;True-3&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;throw&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;TypeError&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;Param must be an object that has the `hostname` attribute&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name=&quot;True-4&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name=&quot;True-5&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a name=&quot;True-6&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;//do something useful&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name=&quot;True-7&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 31 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://mikeborozdin.com/post/writing-a-public-js-library-validate-your-arguments</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://mikeborozdin.com/post/writing-a-public-js-library-validate-your-arguments</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Practical Functional Programming in JavaScript</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;JavaScript is a multi-paradigm language with rich functional programming capabilities. Functional programming does not have to be difficult or hugely theoretical. Quite the opposite &amp;ndash; it can help you to solve the most common programming challenges in a more concise and elegant fashion.&lt;/p&gt;  

&lt;p&gt;In this video I focus on working with arrays in JavaScript. Normally, when dealing with arrays a developer would write a for loop and mutate a variable or two. However, JavaScript already comes with functions, such as, &lt;code&gt;every()&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;filter()&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;map()&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;reduce()&lt;/code&gt;, etc. that help you to write better code for array operations. &lt;!-- more --&gt;.

&lt;p&gt;I also demonstrate how you can combine those functions together in order to encapsulate complex data operations . We analyse performance of some operations and show how certain issues can be solved by using 3rd party libraries, such as &lt;a href=&quot;http://danieltao.com/lazy.js/&quot;&gt;lazy.js&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/facebook/immutable-js&quot;&gt;Immutable.js&lt;/a&gt; Finally, I illustrate how functional programming can become only better in EcmaScript 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube.com/embed/hWWr2fex2Tc&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 16 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://mikeborozdin.com/post/practical-functional-programming-in-javascript</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://mikeborozdin.com/post/practical-functional-programming-in-javascript</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Joy and Benefits of Codefest</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I have already &lt;a href=&quot;http://ncredinburgh.com/blog/posts/information-sharing-in-software-development&quot;&gt;blogged&lt;/a&gt; about the ways to share expertise and knowledge inside your organisation However, there is one more way. That’s something we call a codefest or hackathon. Codefest is an opportunity to work for two days on any project you like using any technology of your choice. Also, it’s a chance to work with people you don’t have on your project. This blog post is available &lt;a href=&quot;http://ncredinburgh.com/blog/posts/joy-and-benefits-of-codefest&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;on my company’s blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://mikeborozdin.com/post/joy-and-benefits-of-codefest</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://mikeborozdin.com/post/joy-and-benefits-of-codefest</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Information Sharing in Software Development</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Where IT organisations have heterogeneous technical environments it is not always possible to know what your colleagues are working on and which challenges they are facing. This blog post will discuss various ways to share information in an IT organisation. The article was written for company’s blog &lt;a href=&quot;http://ncredinburgh.com/blog/posts/information-sharing-in-software-development&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;where you can read it now&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://mikeborozdin.com/post/information-sharing-in-software-development</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://mikeborozdin.com/post/information-sharing-in-software-development</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A Code Review Is More Useful Than You Think</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, I came across a situation which once again proved the immense value in having code reviews. I was working on a tricky part of an application that involved substantial design work. As part of our &#39;Definition of Done&#39;, I had to submit my code for a peer review. The review turned out to be invaluable - after all, it&#39;s always useful to get the second pair of eyes to look at your work.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;I wrote this article for my &lt;a class=&quot;more&quot; href=&quot;http://ncredinburgh.com/blog/posts/a-code-review-is-more-useful-than-you-think&quot;&gt;company’s blog where&lt;/a&gt; you can read it now.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 08 Jun 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://mikeborozdin.com/post/a-code-review-is-more-useful-than-you-think</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://mikeborozdin.com/post/a-code-review-is-more-useful-than-you-think</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>My Agile Journey</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;There can be debates whether the Agile Software Development processes have become mainstream or not, but most of the software development houses are trying to adopt the Agile practices. Yet, coming from academia or, say, a less agile environment, such practices can be misunderstood.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;In this post, I am going to tell how I have become an avid agile practitioner and what has helped in that glorious journey. &lt;!-- more --&gt; My journey started in December 2011 when I finished my Master’s got my first full time job as a Software Developer at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cloudreach.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Cloudreach Limited&lt;/a&gt;. Of course, I had a couple of internships under my belt, and was running this blog, but I clearly didn’t have any experience of working in a team on commercial software. I must admit though I was still interested not only programming languages and technologies, but also in processes. Yet, I only had, say, some textbook knowledge, and was slightly scared to write tests before code. I remember though that while working on some university project I was saying to myself that I must write some unit tests, or otherwise, my code would become a buggy mess.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;The times they are a changing. Now, I can’t allow myself to write a piece of code without writing a test first. So, I’ll try to list the thing which have helped to become comfortable to Agile, and which I have noticed on my journey.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;h2&gt;Proper Mentorship Helps. Yet, You Must Be Open For New Things.&lt;/h2&gt;  &lt;p&gt;First of all, I would hardly be able to embrace Agile without the help of my more experienced colleagues. Thank you guys! Of course, one can read books, and various online resources, but it’s crucial to be able to ask someone a question, and check whether you are on a right track or not. In total, I was assisted in the following ways:&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;ul&gt;   &lt;li&gt;A training project that can give a developer a kick start with the Agile, as well as with some new technology. Since, it’s just a training project it eliminates all possible stress and allows focusing on learning new things &lt;/li&gt;    &lt;li&gt;Code reviews are an efficient way of learning from your peers, and also getting to know other parts of the application. So, try to get your code reviewed, and use a chance to review someone else’s code. I wrote a bit on the benefits of code reviews and the ways of conducting them in &lt;a href=&quot;http://devblog.cloudreach.co.uk/2012/08/asynchronous-code-reviews-as-efficient.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;    &lt;li&gt;Regular catch-ups with a more experienced colleague. In other words, try to get a mentor who works with you and observes your progress. Also, don’t view mentorship as a one-way process. A good mentor will be keen to get your feedback and react accordingly. &lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt;  &lt;p&gt;The last, but not the least, be open to new things. People can be naturally resistant to changes, and it’s essential to keep that in mind when thinking about the customer, yet, yourself should not be discouraged from doing something in a new way.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;h2&gt;Scrum Is Easy To Understand&lt;/h2&gt;  &lt;p&gt;Just recently I came across an &lt;a href=&quot;http://java.dzone.com/articles/why-scrum-won&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; which said that Scrum had achieved its solid position today mainly due to its simplicity. Thinking retrospectively, I would say that this is indeed true. Moreover, this is one of the factors that has helped to adopt the agile quite easily.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;Moreover, things like daily stand-ups and sprint retrospectives allow you to know what everyone is doing, and have your say if something does not go very well.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;h2&gt;Don’t Be Scared of Test-Driven Development&lt;/h2&gt;  &lt;p&gt;Writing tests before code might sound strange at first, but it’s indeed worth doing that. It not only makes your code more reliable, but also dramatically improves its maintainability. Indeed, the book that assisted me in embracing TDD was called ‘&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.growing-object-oriented-software.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Growing Object-Oriented Software Guided By Tests’&lt;/a&gt;. There is a popular argument against TDD which says that it slows down development. In fact, it speeds it up. Try writing a complex application that interacts with a few external system with no tests – it will fail to work at first, and you will struggle to debug it.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;Finally, don’t focus on testing method per se, put emphasis on testing behaviour of your application and its parts. Adopt &lt;a href=&quot;http://dannorth.net/introducing-bdd/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Behaviour-Driven Development&lt;/a&gt;, and pair it with &lt;a href=&quot;http://rubylearning.com/blog/2010/10/05/outside-in-development/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Outside-in Development.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;I also gave a &lt;a href=&quot;http://vimeo.com/46619279&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/a&gt; in Glasgow, UK, and wrote a &lt;a href=&quot;http://devblog.cloudreach.co.uk/2012/05/behaviour-driven-development-in-net.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; about Outside-In Behaviour Driven Development.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;h2&gt;It’s More About Techniques Rather Than Underlying Tools&lt;/h2&gt;  &lt;p&gt;Indeed, you can work with a programming language whose limitation doesn’t allow for having a generic mocking framework. Is it a reason not to use mock objects in your tests? Not all! After all, it doesn’t take a lot of time to write mock objects by hand. Once again, the benefits of doing that will hugely outweigh that little time you spend on it.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;h2&gt;Transfer Your Knowledge As You Go&lt;/h2&gt;  &lt;p&gt;There is no better way to ensure that you understand a concept than explaining it to someone else. Feel free to tell about your Agile successes to fellow developers. Don’t be afraid to blog, and speak at public events. You will not only improve your understanding of the Agile methodology, but spread the word about it. Needless to say, it will also help you to build up your professional reputation.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;h2&gt;It’s A Never Ending Journey&lt;/h2&gt;  &lt;p&gt;Having called myself ‘an avid Agile practitioner’ in the beginning of the article, I believe there are still tons to be learnt. After all, we should try to learn something every day.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 20 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://mikeborozdin.com/post/my-agile-journey</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://mikeborozdin.com/post/my-agile-journey</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
